Okay, moving on to cerebrovascular disease.
This is a neurologic deficit that arises due to cerebrovascular compromise.
It's usually due to ischemia, or a decreased blood flow to the brain,
but it can also be due to hemorrhage into the brain.
Now, the first example would be global cerebral ischemia,
but before we go there, why don't we just highlight a paradigm.
So here's cerebrovascular disease, and of course it can be due to ischemia,
or it can be due to hemorrhage.
Now, when you have ischemia, that ischemia can be focal,
or it can be global.
And by focal, we mean that it involves a region of the brain,
and by global, we mean that it diffusely involves the entire brain.
And so global is called global cerebral ischemia,
and that's what your text is referring to here.
Now, how would you get global cerebral ischemia?
Well, you could get it with low perfusion to the brain.
For example, if you have atherosclerosis of a large vessel that's going into the brain,
this would then decrease the amount of blood going into the brain,
giving you a global cerebral ischemia.
You could also see it with acute decrease in blood flow, for example, with shock.
This would then reduce the overall amount of blood going into the brain.
Similarly, we could see it with anemia.
Again, with anemia, we'd have less oxygen going into the brain globally.
And finally, in very high yield, you can see it with repeated episodes of hypoglycemia.
Recall that glucose is an essential energy source for the brain.
And so if you get hypoglycemia, that will globally affect the entire brain,
creating a global cerebral ischemia.
Now, the clinical features of global cerebral ischemia depend on the severity of the ischemia.
So it can be mild, moderate, or severe.
When it's mild, you get transient confusion with a complete recovery.
The classic example would be an insulinoma.
When patients have an insulinoma, the blood sugar goes down, they get confusion,
you give them back glucose, and the confusion resolves.
So that's an example of mild global ischemia.
In severe global ischemia, you get diffuse necrosis of the brain due to the ischemia,
and the patient probably wouldn't survive.
However, if they did survive, they'd go on to a vegetative state.
With moderate global ischemia, you get infarcts in watershed areas.
The watershed areas are those regions that are fed by the very end of a circulation.
So, for example, the region fed by the very end of the anterior cerebral artery,
or the very end of the middle cerebral artery.
So these are watershed areas, and we can get infarctions in these areas with moderate global ischemia.
In addition, we can get damage to highly vulnerable regions.
For example, the pyramidal neurons of the cortex.
These are neurons present in layers 3, 5, and 6 of the cortex.
Recall that the cortex on histology has multiple layers,
and we call them pyramidal neurons because they have a triangular appearance.
Now imagine if this is the layers of the cortex,
and we get damage to layers 3, layers 5, and layers 6,
then this is going to create a line of necrosis,
and so this is also known as cortical laminar necrosis.
And board examiners like to go after this, so you should be aware of it.
Cortical laminar necrosis.
Now in addition, another vulnerable region would be the pyramidal neurons of the hippocampus.
Remember that the hippocampus is in the temporal lobe,
and its job is to transfer information to your long-term memory.
And so with moderate global ischemia,
you can also get damage to the pyramidal neurons of the hippocampus.
And the third area that is highly vulnerable is the Purkinje layer of the cerebellum.
So with moderate global ischemia, you could also get cerebellar signs.
Moving on to ischemic stroke, let's go back to our paradigm.
Here's cerebrovascular disease.
Remember that it can be due to ischemia or hemorrhage,
and when it's due to ischemia, that can be global or focal.
Now when you have focal ischemia, that again involves one region of the brain,
it then creates focal neurologic deficits.
If the focal neurologic deficits last less than 24 hours,
then we call that a transient ischemic attack.
And if it lasts greater than 24 hours, then we call that an ischemic stroke.
And so that's what your text is saying here when it says that ischemic stroke is regional ischemia
that results in focal neurologic deficits.
If it's greater than 24 hours, you call it a stroke.
And if it's less than 24 hours, you call it a transient ischemic attack.
Focusing on ischemic stroke, there are three ways by which you can develop an ischemic stroke.
The first is thrombotic.
And the idea here is that you've got a blood vessel feeding the cortex,
and here's the cortex out here, you've got atherosclerosis within the blood vessel.
This atherosclerotic plaque ruptures.
That exposes subendothelial collagen and the necrotic debris within the plaque,
resulting in formation of a thrombus.
So now you cut the blood supply.
When you cut this blood supply, you're then going to get infarction way out in the periphery of the cortex,
and this infarction will be a pale infarction.
Now the second type of stroke will be an embolic stroke.
And the idea here is that you've got your blood vessel feeding the cortex.
A thromboembolus, for example, from the left heart, comes in and lodges within this blood vessel.
That cuts the blood supply long enough for the neurons to die,
but then this thrombus gets lysed, and then blood goes back in,
which then results in a hemorrhagic infarction here at the periphery of the cortex.
And again, that's called an embolic stroke.
Now let's briefly visit these in the text, then we'll come back to the third cause of ischemic stroke.
And so we say that a thrombotic stroke arises due to rupture of an atherosclerotic plaque.
Remember that atherosclerotic plaques usually develop at branch points of arteries.
Now, this will then result in a pale infarct at the periphery of the cortex, as I've already explained.
And here's a picture just showing you a very, very early infarction.
This is all normal here.
And then you can kind of see here that this is a little bit discolored,
and so this region here is about to undergo infarction.
But again, the point that I'm trying to illustrate here is that you get a pale infarct at the periphery of the cortex.
The second type of stroke would be an embolic stroke.
Here you have a thromboembolus that arises usually from the left side of the heart, classically in the context of atrial fibrillation,
and that goes and lodges into the blood vessel, usually the middle cerebral artery.
This will then result in a hemorrhagic infarct at the periphery of the cortex.
Now, board examiners like you to understand that when you have a thrombotic stroke, for example here,
then you are going to get a pale infarction.
And when you have an embolic stroke, for example here, then you are going to get a hemorrhagic infarction.
And you could ask the question, why? What's the difference?
Well, notice that when you have a thrombotic stroke, you rupture the atherosclerotic plaque and you get a thrombus.
Now, of course, the body will try to lyse that thrombus.
However, because the plaque is present and it is ruptured, you'll quickly just reform the thrombus.
So no matter how many times you try to lyse this, it's just going to reform.
And so you won't be able to send blood into this region, and so therefore you'll get a pale stroke.
However, with an embolic stroke, this embolus can easily be lyced.
And once it's lyced, then the blood will be able to return back, and that's what's going to create the hemorrhagic stroke.
So it's high yield to know, again, that in a thrombotic stroke, you get a pale infarction,
but that in an embolic stroke, you get a hemorrhagic infarction.
Now, the third way by which you can get an ischemic stroke is called a lacunar stroke.
And the idea here is that this involves the small blood vessels of the brain that undergo highline arteriolosclerosis.
Of course, highline arteriolosclerosis would occur with benign hypertension or with diabetes.
And when this occurs, this will decrease the blood going through those small blood vessels and will result in a lacunar stroke.
Now, the idea here is that if this is a small blood vessel, and you create highline arteriolosclerosis,
you then thicken the wall, making the lumen more narrow.
This will then result in less blood flow being able to go through this small blood vessel
and will result in a little area of infarction, which is in the region being fed by this small blood vessel.
Now, this then would, of course, be resorbed, producing a small little cystic region.
And they call this a lacunar stroke because it produces small little circular areas that look like lakes.
And the word lacunar actually means lake.
Now, let's use this image to highlight an important point.
Here's the circle of Willis.
And the middle cerebral artery would be running this way and eventually would go out and feed the surface of the cortex.
Now, recall that from the middle cerebral artery, you have these small little tiny branches that come out
and feed the deep structures of the brain.
These little blood vessels are called lenticulostriate vessels.
And lacunar strokes most often occur in these tiny little blood vessels,
which then results in highline arteriolosclerosis and then results in these little lake-like areas of infarction.
And so classically, lacunar strokes will be present in the deep structures of the brain.
These are the deep structures of the brain here and will usually involve the lenticulostriate blood vessels.
And that's what I say here in the text, that it's secondary to highline arteriolosclerosis
and that it most commonly involves the lenticulostriate blood vessels.
Here's a picture of a lacunar stroke just to remind you that you get these small little lake-like areas
within the deep structures of the brain.
When you have an ischemic stroke, this will lead to liquefactive necrosis of the brain.
And one of the earliest findings on microscopy will be that you will see red neurons.
This is particularly high yield for board exams.
They'd like you to know that the earliest change is red neurons
and that it takes about 12 hours for those red neurons to develop.
Now, after the cells die, you'll eventually get inflammation.
And so the inflammation will first be neutrophils and then be macrophages.
But, of course, in the brain, the macrophages are called the microglial cells.
And then, of course, after the first week of inflammation,
you'll then go into a healing phase, which is granulation-like tissue.
It's not exactly granulation tissue, but it's sort of granulation-like.
And then the eventual result, after about a month,
will be that you'll have a fluid-filled cystic space surrounded by gliosis.
And gliosis simply refers to the reactive astrocytes
that will line that cystic space with this gliotic connective tissue.
Now, let me just remind you that the sequence here is very similar
to the sequence that we had within the heart,
if you remember your cardiac lectures.
Remember there I told you one day, one week, one month.
And the idea here is that it takes about a day for the cells to die.
And before that, you would see red neurons.
Once the cells die, you'll have a phase of inflammation
that is from one day to one week.
And it will begin with the neutrophils.
And then, eventually, the microglial cells will come in.
And then from one week to one month, you'll have this granulation tissue.
It's not exactly granulation tissue in the brain,
but it's sort of granulation tissue-like.
But then, eventually, that will result in this cystic space.
So you'll have a cyst.
And, of course, there will be gliosis with astrocytes around that cyst.
And so that's particularly important that the final stage is a gliotic cyst.
Now, there's two areas that board examiners like to focus on here.
The first is that you get red neurons.
And so these are the red or pink neurons that are present
as these cells are dying and undergoing apoptosis.
And, of course, this would occur at about 12 hours
and would be present for up to the first 24 hours.
And then the examiners like you to know
that the very end stage is a cystic lesion,
which is surrounded by gliosis.
And, of course, the center is cystic
because it underwent liquefactive necrosis.
Now, the next topic is intracerebral hemorrhage.
But before we discuss this, let's go back.
You have cerebrovascular disease.
And this can be due to ischemia or it can be due to hemorrhage.
When it's due to ischemia, that can be focal or that can be global.
And we've already discussed both focal and global.
So now we're going to discuss hemorrhage.
And there's two types of hemorrhage.
There's intracerebral hemorrhage or hemorrhage into the brain parenchyma.
And then there's subarachnoid hemorrhage,
which is hemorrhage into the subarachnoid space.
And both of these, again, are a type of cerebrovascular disease.
With that background in mind,
intracerebral hemorrhage is bleeding into the brain.
It's classically due to rupture of Charcot-Bouchard microaneurysms,
which is a complication of hypertension.
And the basal ganglia is the most common site.
Let's use this image to clarify some of what we just said.
So here is the circle of Willis.
The middle cerebral artery is coming up and feeding the surface of the cortex.
And recall that you've got these perforating vessels coming here,
which are called the lenticulostriate vessels.
Now remember that the lenticulostriate blood vessels can undergo
highline arteriolosclerosis in the face of hypertension.
And that highline arteriolosclerosis will decrease the blood supply through the vessel
and could result in lacunar infarctions, as we've already described.
However, another possibility would be that you could actually get
highline arteriolosclerosis that weakens the wall of these blood vessels,
so that the blood vessels develop something called Charcot-Bouchard microaneurysms.
Now those Charcot-Bouchard microaneurysms can rupture.
And when these rupture, you'll then get bleed within the parenchyma of the brain.
Here's a picture highlighting that the basal ganglia is the most common site.
And again, of course, that's because you've got these lenticulostriate blood vessels
that are feeding the deep structures of the brain.
Moving on to subarachnoid hemorrhage,
this is when you have bleeding into the subarachnoid space.
It presents a sudden headache, quote-unquote the worst headache of my life,
with nuchal rigidity.
Were an LP to be performed, it would show xanthochromia,
which basically refers to a yellow tinge to the CSF
because of bilirubin breakdown products.
Now when you have a subarachnoid hemorrhage,
this is relatively easy on examinations
because you'll see a bleed on the bottom of the brain.
So really, this is the only thing that gives you a bleed on the bottom of the brain.
So they show you the brain upside down
with blood sitting on the basal surface,
and that then would tell you that there's a subarachnoid hemorrhage.
Now very high yield to note that the most frequent cause
of a subarachnoid hemorrhage is rupture of a bary aneurysm.
Recall that bary aneurysms are thin-walled saccular outpouchings
that are most frequently present in the anterior circle of Willis,
particularly at the branch points of the anterior communicating artery.
Very high yield examiners like you to know
that the most frequent location of bary aneurysm is in the anterior circle of Willis
at the branch points of the anterior communicating artery.
Now the idea here is that these bary aneurysms can easily rupture
because they lack a media layer.
Illustrating this, here is a blood vessel with an intima, a media, and an adventitia.
So this is one wall, and here would be another wall
where you have an intima, a media, and an adventitia,
and of course blood is flowing this way.
Now what happens in a bary aneurysm is that when you get branching,
you get turning of the intima at the branch point
and turning of the adventitia at the branch point.
However, the media fails to develop where the branch is.
It would be present as you move further down into the blood vessel,
but it fails to develop at the branch point.
Now when it fails to develop at the branch point,
this then results in a weak wall here,
and so you'd get a saccular outpouching of this blood vessel,
which is called the bary aneurysm,
and of course eventually this can rupture.
And so it's very high yield to note
that the bary aneurysm lacks a media layer,
which then makes it susceptible to rupture.
One last point that often shows up on exams,
and that is bary aneurysms are associated with Marfan syndrome,
and they are also associated with autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease,
which again is the adult form of polycystic kidney disease.
Here's a picture of a bary aneurysm.
Here you've got a normal blood vessel,
and then you can see this saccular outpouching here occurring at a branch point.
And that concludes our section on cerebrovascular disease.